Welcome to this new lecture of the course
and this is quite special. I happen to
be on camera because in this lecture
what is going to build is a program that
detects objects, moving objects in front
of a computer webcam and then what it
does it record the time that the object
enters the webcam, so the video frame
and the time when the object exited the
video frame, so now there is a moving
object in frame and if I go away you see
that there's no green rectangle now in
the video. And now I show up again, move
out again, and so on. So we're going to
build this application from scratch
using Python and yeah we have a lot of
things to learn such as image processing
and video processing as well, and so on.
And lastly what we do then if you press
q for quit, what you get is a graph and
as I said the graph will show the times
where the object entered the frame so
we're dealing with an interactive graph
here and yeah, this are the times when
the object entered the webcam like this
one, this one here, and here it lasted
longer, and so on. This can be a great
application if you want to detect objects.
you get throw, you can put this
application of this Python program in
a Raspberry Pi server for instance
which is a small server and you can put
it somewhere and maybe want to detect
animals. You may want to know when this
animal is entering the frame and whem
it is exiting, or with people as well if
there is the case. So, yeah, this is
the program and I hope you enjoyed. we have
quite a lot of codes to write, so let's
get started and I'll talk to you
in the next lecture.