Hey! Here we are again and in this lecture we
will continue building our real-world
motion detection program. Now before I go
and write the code ,I would first like to
explain to you the architecture of
the program that we'll be building. So how
this program is able to detect motion in
the video. And I assume you already know
how to build this script, so we built
this in the previous lectures, and what
the script does is that in case you've
missed it. Hey! So what this does is it
triggers the video as you saw from the
computer webcam, so we were processing
frames here in this while loop and so on.
So you know this I will not go through
them right now, so what we need to do
next is we need to process those frames
that are being iterated in this while
loop, and I've got some pictures here to
illustrate my ideas, my concepts. Let me
go to the directory where they are located.
So what this motion detection
program will do is it will trigger the
webcam just like our current script does
and one condition for the program to
work well is that once you trigger the
webcam the first frame of the video
should be a static background.
So if you're planning to use this
program let's say you'll set up a webcam
on a laptop or as Raspberry Pi server. Let's
say you want to detect the movement of
of a certain animal in an area, so first
you'd want to capture, to trigger
the camera while the background is
static and then you want to use this
background as a base image so that you
can compare the other images and then
Python can detect if there is a change
between the first frame
and the next frames.
So that's one thing you need to do
and so this is an example of background.
And then something, the animal will
appear on your camera. Okay, and then what
you have to write in your script in the
program is that first we would want to
gray out this image, so the background
image at the current frame of the camera.
So you'll store the first frame of the
video capture in a variable, and then you
will convert that frame to a grayscale
image and then the while loop will
go through the current frames and you'll do
the same for the current frames, so you'll
convert them to grayscale, and then what
you do to these two grayscale images of
the current iteration of the loop, you'll
apply the difference between them.
So this is a difference an example of
a difference frame, of a delta frame if you
can say like that. In this particular
image you'll notice that behind me, there
is a lamp of the room and normally you
wouldn't be able to see the lamp, but Python
is actually making the difference
between the frame where I was appearing
and the background frame where the lamp
is visible, so it comes up with this gray
image where each pixel has a certain
value, so it has some intensity values.
All right, so that means for instance the
the high intensity values like this
one where I am means there is
potential motion in this area here, while
the blacks areas imply there is no
motion, but you also see some light black
pixels here because when i when I appear
on camera there is shadow behind me and so on.
But we will apply something else later on
which is called the threshold, so we'll
basically say that if you see adifference
in the delta frame, in the frame
that I just showed you, if you see
a difference of more than 100 intensity
convert that pixels, those pixels
to white pixels, okay.
And for pixels that are below the
threshold convert them to black, okay.
So you come up with the outline of the
object that is moving in the camera,
in the frame. So we're doing all these
processes, inside the while loop and then
once we have calculated the threshold frame
inside the loop what we'll do to the
current frame is will find the contours
of the white objects in the frame, okay.
So for this particular image we would have
contours around this object here, and the
contours around this, and around this is as well,
and then we'll write a for loop that will
iterate through all the contours of the
current frame, okay, it will go to this contur,
to this, to this, and to this one, and then
inside that loop what we will do, is we will
check if the area of the contours, so this
for example has an area of let's say 500
pixels, so if the area of the
contour is more than 500 pixels for
example, then consider this as a moving
moving object. If there is let's say less
than 500 like this one here is probably
20 pixels let's say, this will not be
considered a moving object, okay, I hope
that makes sense, and then what we'll do
next is we'll draw a rectangle around
the contours that were greater than the
minimum area and I will show those
rectangles in original image, so in the
color version of the current frame, and that
means we will see a rectangle in the
video while the video is playing
we will see rectangle around the object.
Later on we will detect the times that
the object, the moving object entered
the background, the video frame, and the time
that the object exited the background.
But for now let's simply focus on
detecting the object, the moving object
in the video. Okay.
Let's go back to the script.
Close this and this and this. Okay and let's
remove some unnecessary lines here.
So we had the a variable here which we
created because we wanted to see how
many frames we had in the video, so we
don't need that anymore, and we don't
need the script to stop for three seconds.
So I remove the time.sleep.
And this one as well. Okay, and now here the
first part is the most trickiest one.
We need to figure out a way to store the
current frame of the video so as soon as
the video starts we want to store that
Numpy array in a variable and have that
variable static, so we don't want to
change the value of the variable while
the while loop runs in the script.
The way to do that is we would first
need to create a variable for the frame,
for the first frame, so we need to assign it
a None value, so None is a special Python
data type that allows you to create a
a variable and assign nothing to it but
you have the variable there, so if you call
this variable later Python will not say
variable is not defined. Okay, if you
don't understand it, please hold on and
you will get it in just a while. And what you
need to do now is to write a conditional
and apply a continue statement in there.
Let me write the conditional first and
then I'll explain to you what this does.
So we want to check if the first frame
is None and if it is None we will assign
the first frame the gray frame.
So what this does is that the scrip will
run, the video will be triggered and then the
while loop will start to run and it will get
the first frame of the video, and it will
store it in this frame variable,
and this frame variable will be
converted into a gray frame and then we
say if the first frame is None, which is
true in the first iteration of the loop
this is true, so the first frame is
actually None because we assigned None
here, assign the gray numpy to the
first frame. So the first frame will get
the grayscale image which represents the
very first frame of the video. So this
happens in the very first iteration of the
loop, okay? But then, what will happen is
Python will execute these other lines of
code and then it will go to the second loop
and what Python will do is it will grab
the second frame of the video, okay?
Let's say the first frame was a background
image, then suddenly an object appears in
the camera, in front of the camera so
Python will grab the numpy array that
contains that object, so the second frame
and this frame will be converted to gray
and then here we say if first frame is None,
the first frame variable will get the
first frame of the video and once we
have grabbed the first frame we don't
want this other lines of code to be
executed because here we will have, you
know, we'll apply the difference between
frames and we will blurry the frames and
so on, so we don't want these to be
executed, instead we want Python to go to
the beginning of the loop and continue
with the second frame. To do that we need
to go and write continue here. So this means
continue to the beginning of the loop
and don't go and around the rest of the
code, okay, so the first frame is None.
The first frame gets this value of the first
image of the video and then goes to the
next iteration, and then the next
iteration what will do, it will grab
the second frame of the video and then it
will calculate the gray version of that
frame and then it goes again to the
conditional, and in this case is the
first frame None? No, it's not because
the first frame got the value of the
gray image
in the first iteration of the
while loop, so this lines here will not
be executed at the second iteration of
the loop, okay? Great.
That means we can now apply Delta frame,
so we can calculate the difference
between the first frame and the current
frame of the image. So the first frame is
the first frame variable and the
current frame is a gray variable,
but before that we would like to do
something to the current frame of the
image. We want to apply a Gaussian blur
to the image. And a dot here.
So the reason we want to apply Gaussian
blur is that we want to blur the image
so we want to make it blurry so to
smooth it because that removes noise and
increases accuracy in the calculation
of the difference, so this gets
parameter the image you want to blur.
So we are passing the gray image
here and we're storing the blurry version of
the image in a gray image again, and then
we have another parameter which comes as
a tuple and here we need to pass a width
and height of a Gaussian kernel, so which
is basically the parameters of the
blurriness, but 21 would be accepted numbers.
And you also need a number, last parameter
so that would be the standard deviation
and pass zero. Zero here is also commonly
used. If you want to learn about them you
can go through the documentation but
these values would be good. So we're
making the gray image blurry here, then
down here now we need to compare the
first frame of the image, so the
background with the current frame.
Let's call this delta frame and that would
be equal to cv2.absdifference so
absolute difference
between the first frame
and the current frame which is gray.
Note that the first frame will also be
a gray version, a blurry gray
version actually, so we are comparing
here two blurriede grayscale images, okay?
And what this will give us is another
image, okay? And actually I would like to
show that image here on the screen.
Cv2image show Delta frame. Let's see what
we'll get out of this. And before running
the script I'll disappear from the view
first and then will appear again.
Let's see. Okay, nothing happened because.
I forgot to enter the name of the window
Let's call this delta frame and let's
say gray frame for this. Now let me run
it again. And here so this is the blurred
grayscale version, this one here and we
have the difference, okay, so you can see
the lamp behind me in the delta frame. Great.
Press the Q key and quit the video now
if you if I want to print just to check
the delta frame, this will allow us to
see the difference between intensities
of the corresponding pixels so let's see.
And if I quit this now
here we go. So what we have here five
means there is no difference, so in this
area there's no motion probably but then
you have 174 which is quite white,
so that means Python will classify
this as motion. Okay, that was just to show
you the values of the delta frame. What
we need now is to classify these values.
So let's say we want to assign
a threshold, so let's say if you have
values that are more than 30, so if
the difference between the first frame
and the current frame is more than 30,
we will classify that as white.
So we will say there's probably motioning
in those pixels, so there's an object in
those pixels, and if the difference is
less than thirty we'll assign it black
pixels, okay? So we can do that so we are
here, we can do that using the
threshold method of the cv2 library.
Let's say thresh_delta equals to
cv2.threshold, and what this expects is a image
that you want to threshold and then you
want to specify a threshold limit.
So 30, we said 30. And what color do
you want to assign to the values that
are more than 30? Well we want to saw
in a white color which corresponds to
the 255 value, okay? And you also need
one more argument here which is the
threshold method. There are quite a few
methods out there, but we are using
this method here, so threshold binary.
You can experiment with others if you like.
Great and now let's see how this thresh
Delta frame will look like. Cv2.imshow
threshold frame.
Okay, thresh_delta.
Great, let's see!
apparently I wrote this wrongly. Delta
frame, not frame Delta. And one more
typo in line 19 which is here, cv2, okay.
Let's hope this time will work, and yet
another error. And this time I've missed
something here. Okay, this method here so
the threshold method actually returns
a tuple with two values, and the first
value is it's needed when you use other
threshold methods, so the first item or
the topple basically suggests a value
for threshold if you're using other
methods, but for financial binary you
only need to access the second item of
the tuple which is the actual frame
that is returned from the threshold
method, so you want to access the second
item of the tuple. Okay, I promise this
is a last error. Great, finally! And this
is the threshold frame, so you can see my
outline there, but you also see some
shadows. So I am being detected as an
object, but my shadows as well are
being detected as on objects too. Okay.
So you get the idea. Now we can go right
away and use this Thresh Delta frame
which I called it thresh Delta. I should
call it the thresh frame, you know, just
for name consistency. So we can go ahead
now and create contours of the white
objects in the thresh frame, but before that
I would like to do something else.
I would like to dilate those areas.
So I want to remove the black holes
from those big white areas in the
image, so basically I want to smooth my
threshold frame, and to do that you need
to use the dilate method of the cv2
library, so let's say we want to change
the threshold frame. Cv2.dilate. Again you
want to pass the threshold frame there. Now
if you have a kernel array and you want
this process to be very sophisticated
you'd pass that array in here. We don't
have any and we don't need one, so you
need to pass None for this parameter and
there's yet another parameter here.
Iterations and let's say two, so this
defines how many times do you want to go
through the image to remove those holes.
So the bigger this number is, the smoother
this image will be. Okay. Now let me
check it quickly. Oh yeah, I changed
the name earlier, but I didn't change it
here in the imshow method. Thresh frame.
Okay, so you can probably notice that
the areas, the white areas are smoother now
so if I go away you'll only notice a few areas
that are there because of my shadow, so
it seems to be working so far. Let's quit
it now. Great, so we've got these three
frames and what's next? Well next is we
need to find the contours of this
dilated threshold frame. Regarding
contour detection with openCV you have
two methods, so you have a find contours
and a draw contours method. And with the
find conturs method what you do is you
find the contours in your image and you
store them in a tuple, on the other hand
the draw contours method draws contours in
an image, so in this case what we want to do
is we want to find the contours and then
we want to check if the area of this
contour, so let's say you have a contour
like a circle and so you want to find
the area that this also defines, so you
want to store those contours in
a tuple and that's quite a weird syntax
here, but bear with me.
So you want to write underscore comma
cnts comma and another underscore.
And if you were in OpenCV2 you
wouldn't need the first underscore and
the first comma, so you'd have this in
OpenCV2 with Python 2. If you
have OpenCv3 with Python 3 this
is what you need to write. Okay, and that
would be equal to cv2.findContours.
And then you want to pass afraid that
you want to find the contours for. And it's
good to actually use the copy of the frame
so you don't want to modify the
threshold frame, so use copy here.
So this is the first parameter, the frame
you want to find contours from, and then
you have the method retrieve external.
So you want to draw the external contours
of the objects that you'll be fining in the
image, and you've got yet another
argument. Chain_aprox_simple. So this is
approximation method that OpenCV will
apply for retriving the conturs, great.
So what we have is we are iterating
through the current frame so we are
blurring it, and converting it to
grayscale, and find a data frame,
and apply the thresholds, so the black
black and white image, and then we find
all the contours of the objects, of the
distinct objects in this image so if
you've got two white continuous areas in
your image but they are distinct, you'll get
two contours, so one contour for each of
the areas, and these corners will be stored
in this, cnts variable. So we're talking
about the current frame, and that's what
we want to do, is we want to filter out
these contours, so we want to check that we
want to keep only the contours that are,
let's say that have an area that is
bigger than 100, 1000 pixels. For that you
need to iterate. Let's say for contour
in cnts, and if cv2.contour area of
the contour, so the contour that we are
iterating through, so if this is less
than 1000, continue to the beginning of
the for loop again. So what this means is
let's say Python found three contours and
it will go through the first one and it
will say if the area of this contour, so
we use the contour area of the cv2
library, if the area has less than
1000 pixels, go to the next contour, so go
to the second contour and check again,
and again, and again. Otherwise if the area
is bigger than, or equal to 1000, the next
lines here after the for loop will be
executed. So what do you want to do
if a contour is greater than 1000 pixels?
Well we want to draw the rectangle
surrounding that contour to the
current frame, so make sure you are
inside the for loop,
So these are the parameters that define
the rectangle and that would be equal to
cv2.boundRectangle of the current
contour, so if the contour is equal or
greater than 1000 pixels, so if I it
has an a of equal, or greater
than 1000 pixels, this will be executed.
So we are creating a rectangle and then
we want to draw that rectangle to our
frame, to our current frame so cv2
rectangle, so we already consumed this
method in our face detection lectures.
And here we would want to pass the
color frame. Okay, so that is the frame
and we want to specify x and y here, so these
are the coordinates of upper left corner of
the rectangle. X, y and you want to
specify the coordinates of the right
lower corner of the rectangle as well so
X W, just like that. And also the color of
your rectangle. Let's say green and the width.
Let's say 3, so what we did in these two
lines is that we created this tuple
with this four coordinates and these values,
these will be assigned automatically, so x
and y will get the value from
the rectangle bounding this contour,
this current contour of the for loop.
And then these values will be used to draw
a rectangle in the frame, in the current
frame, and then we want to show that
current frame. So let me edit here.
Image show. Let's call
this color frame. And frame.
Actually this method here is boundingRect.
Let me try the script now.
And cv2 has no attribute find countours.
co here I've got a u there
that shouldn't be there.
Let's try it again. Yep, that's funny.
I tend to mistype this word. Countour area
in line 24 and remover the u. It should be
contour here as well.
okay, countour is not defined again. I've
got another one here, so bear with me.
Try again and yeah, this time seems to be
working. So no objects, objects. No objects,
objects, great. Great, so that's what I
want to teach you in this lecture and
we'll continue in the next lectures
because what we've done so far
is that we can detect that object and we
can draw a rectangle around that object,
but this is not very practical. I mean in
real world it's not enough to just draw a
rectangle around your object
and then that's it.
So what we'll be doing in the next
lecture is will be storing the times
that the object enters the frame and when
the object exits the frame, so we've got some
more lines to add to this code and I
know this code here was quite a lot to
consume, but I hope these are clear now.
If you have any questions please
feel free to ask them and I'll see you
in the next lecture.